so I've been thinking about thinking for
well over 20 years and I think I have
more questions than I do answers and I
like to share some of those questions
with you today now on my journey I've
been doing a lot of research and in 2009
and ran across this report that just
really caught my attention in this
report
it's from the company called the
Millennium project and this organization
consists of well over 500 scientists
researchers academics and business
people from over 50 different countries
and this report is called the state of
future report in the outline of the 15
global challenges facing humanity so the
things you would expect to see clean
water population growth energy are all
on the list it was number 9 that caught
my attention number 9 the capacity to
decide in other words decision making
made it on the list of the global
challenges facing humanity lies is the
case lies decision-making becoming more
challenging with all the information
technology and tools that we have
available to us
wise decision making on this list well
about ten years ago and created this
model it's very simple but I think it
does a good job in explaining both the
problem as well as the opportunity what
we're finding is that most training
teaches people what to think that is it
gives them the processes the procedures
the methodologies and the information
they need to perform a task now this is
very important because we all need a
solid foundation however what to think
is a lot like fast food it's convenient
it's fast it's prepackaged and
oftentimes it's overly processed in the
form of regurgitated ideas and opinions
that do very little to contribute to our
deeper understanding
the world now mass media understands
this politicians certainly understand
this and I believe schools know this
take for example the news they repeat
the same message over and over and over
until we believe it
politicians crap four or five older
coins and repeat those over and over
schools they package content chunk it
and sequence it and then give us a test
to see if we can remember any of it this
makes the question then why are we
surprised when we find people that are
not as creative innovative and
passionate as they could be well this is
where the opportunity comes in we have
to shift our thinking that is in
addition to teaching people what to
think we also need to educate them on
how to think so for example if I teach
you what to think you can take what
you've learned and apply it to a similar
situation however if you learn how to
think you can take what you've learned
and adapt it to a multiple situations in
other words how to think is learning how
to learn or as we like to say it's to
learn unlearn and relearn quickly now my
mission is to help schools as well as
corporations find the optimal balance
between what and how and I've done this
by focusing really on two areas
cognitive neuroscience and computer
science now in cognitive neuroscience
what I'm looking for is how do we learn
that is how do we create new neural
pathways and looking at the impacts that
bias communications education has on
learning and memory and from a computer
science point of view looking for new
technologies that not only allow us to
study decision making but allow us to
create an environment that we can put
people in so they can learn how to think
so we've done this by creating highly
advanced computer-based simulations now
using these simulations we can challenge
participants to make decisions and solve
problems that are similar to the ones
that they face in their own organization
so not only do they learn how to think
about their own organization but we can
capture a significant amount of day
so we can assess their thinking over
time now this is what we found when
people have a lot of training that is a
lot of what to think training and
they're placed in these simulations and
they're confronted the problems that
they face in their real world most
participants resorted to guessing that
is when we give them more data tools
checklist choices their decision-making
did not improve if anything it got worse
so realizing that many of the challenges
that people face today are too big for
just one person we should get our focus
to looking at team performance so here
is our line of thinking we thought if we
can improve team performance how people
collaborate how they solve problems
together we can then improve their
overall thinking and hopefully their
decision-making so let me give you an
example let's say we're all part of a
big organization and a few of us have
been tasked with growing a certain
division of the organization so we get
together and I get it together with you
and I say hey what does growth mean to
you and you say well it's about
profitability and revenue I go to
someone else plays growth mean to you
you might say it is about people and
engagement and another person may say
well it's actually about market share
and price now all these are valid we're
excited to be part something new a new
initiative doing something important for
the organization so we get out there and
make a promise we're going to grow this
division by X percent over this period
in time then we get it back together
roll up our sleeves and start putting
our plans together and that's when it
fits us the realization that we all have
a very different perspective of what a
growth means when that happens conflict
happens we've all felt this I can easily
switch the word growth with community we
all have different perspectives on
community politics Wow lots of
perspectives their family relationships
actually I think there's lenses that
they call Mars and Venus
so realizing that when we feel conflict
because we have different perspectives
this can be demoralizing it can drain
our energy and erode our passion so
after about five years when honestly
felt like boiling the ocean trying to
find skills that improve team
performance I mean we tried everything
we tried teaching people conflict
resolution coaching and mentoring and
gave them checklists and processes and
tools the bottom line none of these
created the sustainable improvement that
we were looking for so when we're
looking for that improvement we decided
to step back and ask a different
question what did type top performers do
finally we found one skill that was
common to all top performers they
developed the ability to ask for the
questions now I know that sounds simple
but what they asked and how they asked
was very different for example many of
them were able to suspend their judgment
just long enough to understand someone
else's perspective and in doing so they
were able to reduce the conflict develop
a common language and create a shared
vision so as the situation evolved so do
their thinking now I know we all ask a
lot of questions and that's a really
good thing we want people to be asking
lots and lots of questions but what we
found however is that most questions are
safe that is they surface what is
already seen or understood they lead to
regurgitated ideas and opinions in other
words most questions that people ask
really surface what is already known now
top performers however they ask
questions that go deep they ask
questions that move us from automatic
and reactionary thinking to deep
thinking ask questions that inspire
creativity fuel passion and lead to
profound ideas and most importantly they
ask questions that spur
- in other words they ask questions that
demystify the unknown and in doing so
open up an ocean of possibilities now
our brain is an amazing searchable
database linking emotions memories
events and experiences together to form
answers to our endless questions the
success of the good answer however
relies on the words we choose our words
have amazing power on our brain how we
use words in framing our questions is
what differentiates a good question from
a bad question let me give you an
example when we saw people put into the
simulation that were confronted with
these challenges and they started to
make decisions the teams that were
struggling would ask what should we do
it was almost as though the options in
front of them were just narrowed down
and they became very short-term focused
whereas other teams would ask what could
we do it was like the ocean of
possibilities opened up to them now the
same is true for the types of questions
we asked herself for example if I ask
why do I always procrastinate my brain
will surely tell me it's because I'm
lazy because they have too much to do I
don't know where to get started however
I slightly reframe that and say how am I
going to get this done my brain will
surely find a better answer now I know
if I was sitting out in where you are
right now I would say so what there's
got to be a lot more to this than just
framing questions well there is I
believe that since we've been taught
what to think for so long that the very
idea of asking a question that triggers
deep thinking evokes so many different
emotions it creates uncertainty fear
anxiety stress these are all very very
real biological reactions to questions
and from a neuroscience perspective to
much of any of these can impair our
learning ability to connect ability
elicits
with one another so what we found is
that the individuals who would embrace
these emotions that is understand that
these are just part of the natural
process and asking good questions and
allowing questions to do their work then
questions can really start to make a
difference so a good question will
expose our bias a good question will
surface our beliefs and oftentimes
questions will expose that we may not
know something as well as we think we do
now these are good things to have happen
because when this happens learning can
take place this is when people can come
connect it this is when they can create
relatedness and understanding and
believe in one another this is when
people can work together to adapt their
thinking so now the good news is that
I've seen kids parents coaches
businesspeople and even politicians
break through these emotional and mental
barriers and learn to become confident
in asking good questions now there are a
lot of challenges in this world we all
have them whether in our business in our
cities in our schools and our families
in our relationships we all have them we
all have a very different lens on what
these challenges are and how to address
them and this is a really good thing
because I believe that most of these
problems are too big for one person and
we really need each other what if what
if you learned how to ask good questions
every day what if tomorrow when you went
to meet with somebody you seek to
understand them instead of trying to be
understood what if before in every
important meeting you took the time to
write down questions that would move the
conversation from the known to the
unknown
what if executives led by questions not
by questioning but asking questions that
inspired others to think about what they
could do
now what they should do what if churches
synagogues mosque ask how long we to
live instead of focusing on whether
others don't do what if parents ask
their kids
what great question did you ask today
instead of asking what did you learn
today with questions you get what you
asked for and in an era in which
computers are getting better at
answering questions we need people who
are getting better at asking questions
thank you